James Everett Perdue Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
James Everett Perdue Papers
1963 - 1991
The professional collection of James E. Perdue, the seventh President of SUNY Oswego and covers the years from 1963 to 1991. Dr. Perdue oversaw the ongoing physical transformation of the campus landscape and growth in its student and faculty ranks. He spearheaded the opening of the academic quad that includes Hewitt, Penfield Library and Lanigan, Mahar and Tyler Halls; several residence halls including what is known as “New Campus”; dining halls; the Culkin administration building and other spaces still of great use.
2 linear feet 3 boxes
State University College (Oswego, N.Y.)
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
2001.015.0001
Collection is open to the public.
James Everett Perdue was the seventh president of S.U.N.Y. Oswego from 1965 until 1977. Under his presidency, S.U.N.Y. Oswego grew in many ways. Dorms, dining halls, Hewitt Union, Penfield Library, the administration building and various academic halls were built. Relations between the college, faculty and students were also improved during the period of student unrest in the early 1970's. Dr. Perdue left S.U.N.Y. Oswego in 1977 to become associate chancellor at S.U.N.Y. and was succeeded by Virginia Radley. Perdue retired in 1983 and spent the next several years involved in various academic projects around the country. In 1991, Dr. Perdue wrote his autobiography.
Dr. James E. Perdue died in 1998.
State University College (Oswego, N.Y.); Oswego (N.Y.); College presidents
Included in the series is an autobiography, photographs, Perdue Inauguration papers, S.U.N.Y. Oswego 125th Anniversary papers, speeches, articles, pamphlets, college memorandum, reports, consultations, correspondence, and information on student unrest at Oswego during the 1970's.
- Autobiography, 1991 (Box-folder 1-1)
  The autobiography of James E. Perdue, "The First Seventy-Five Years 1916-1991: An Autobiography", 375 pages, published in 1991. It details his thoughts on his family and life. Included is correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs and genealogical information. Sections: In the Beginning The First Teaching Position Courtship 1938 The Wedding and After, 1939-1942 A New Home, A New Job, A New Baby The War Years, 1941-1945 Harvard and On, Late November 1943 New York City and Brooklyn Atlantic Sea Duty Home From The Wars The Deanship 1965 1966 1967 1968 1969 1970 1970 Afterthoughts 1971 1972 Europe August 1, 1972 -- Back At Work 1974 1975 1976 1977 1978 1979 1980 1981 1982 1983 1984 1985 1986 1987 1988 1989 1990 1991 Appendix: Perdue Family Heritage -- genealogy information, photographs, correspondence, newspaper clipping.
- Autobiography copy 2, 1991 (Box-folder 1-2)
  "The First Seventy-Five Years 1916-1991: An Autobiography". copy 2
- Photographs, 1960's - 1970's (Box-folder 1-3)
  Several photographs of Perdue in a group, by himself and also a picture taken by Perdue that was used as the cover photo for the S.U.N.Y. Oswego Student Directory 1973-74. The photographss were taken in the 1960's and early 1970's. Others identified in some of the group photos are Janice Cromp, Gary Hoppee, Hilda Bohall, and Taylor Harter. There are 8 photographss total, one a duplicate.
- Perdue Inauguration, 1966 (Box-folder 1-4)
  Materials relating to the inauguration of James Perdue on May 14, 1966, as the 7th president of S.U.N.Y. Oswego. Included are: Invitation to the inauguration. Bifold. 8 1/4" x 5 1/8" Inauguration program. 10 1/4" x 7 1/4". 12 pp. Saturday, May 14, 1966 @ 11:00. Location: Mary V. Lee hall, Oswego, New York. 2 copies. Includes: Processional -- College Band, George J. Cuppernull, Director Presiding -- Charles Yager, Professor of Chemistry The National Anthem Invocation-- The Reverend Frederick R. Mills, Christ Church Anthem "Psalm 150"-- The Symphonic Choir, The College Orchestra, Maurice O. Boyd, Director Remarks-- Samuel B. Gould, President of the State University of New York Presentation of the President -- George M. Penney, Chairman, College Council Installation of the President -- Samuel B. Gould, President of the State University of New York Inaugural Address-- James E. Perdue, President of State University College, Oswego Benediction-- The Reverend Robert Hall, St. Mary's Church Recessional-- College Band. Includes lists of names -- Delegates from Learned Societies, Foundations and Professional Organizations Delegates from Colleges and Universities [inserted in program is supplemental list] Delegates from Colleges and Universities of The State University of New York. Also includes Inaugural Committee members. Inserted in program are six cards [tickets?] measuring 5 1/4" x 2 1/4". The front of each card is printed "Inauguration '66, Spring Weekend". The reverse: Sunday, May 15th, Major Attraction, Louis Armstrong Concert, Lee Hall, 8:00 p.m. Saturday, May 14th, Inaugural Ball, Lakeside Dining Hall, 9:00 p.m. Friday, May 13th, Jam Session ("The Invictas"), Campus School Parking Lot, 10:00 p.m. Friday, May 13th, Symphonic Choir Spring Concert, Sheldon Auditorium, 8:00 p.m. Friday, May 13th, Phi Sig Beauty Contest, Sheldon Auditorium, 4:30 p.m. 2 copies. 6 copies of a booklet. 2 of the copies are in envelopes. Includes: Inaugural Convocation agenda Events of Inaugural Weekend Inaugual Remarks by Samuel B. Gould, President of the State Univeristy of New York. "The Analytic and the Synthetic" by James E. Perdue. 3-page transcript of speech. Expression of gratitude card from Dr. James Everett Perdue "on the occasion of his installation as the Seventh President of State University of New York College at Oswego". 5 3/8" x 4 1/8" 36-page issue of "The Oswegonian". photocopy.
- State University of New York 25th Anniversary, 1973 (1-5)
  State University of New York 25th Anniversary Various materials pertain to the anniversary celebration at Oswego and in Albany at S.U.N.Y.. The celebration at the Oswego campus was to commemorate the 25th year of SUNY campuses. Included is correspondence, pamphlets, conference speakers, memorandum, financial records, speeches, S.U.N.Y. Albany Symposium materials, and conference planning papers. The 25th Anniversary celebration took place at Oswego the weekend of October 8-11, 1973.
- Articles and Pamphlets, 1965 - 1980 (1-6)
  Articles, booklets and pamphlets were either written by Perdue or contain a speech or excerpt by him. There are five booklets written between 1965 and 1980. The Oswegonian. January 15, 1965, article. "Dr. Perdue Named SUCO President". 1970 booklet, "Freedom and Responsibility on Campus" contains two chapters written by Dr.Perdue. Table of Contents: I. Freedom and Responsibility on Campus: An Overview II. The College Communinity: Present Tension and Future Shock III. The Oswego Strike: What Happened? IV. Communications Within the College V. The Changing Process of Education VI. Minority Groups VII. The College Community and Political Action. A Presidential Farewell. Announcement and reservation form. Included here is an 81-page booklet, "Proceedings First Annual Convocation of Distinguished Faculty" with a speech by Dr. Perdue. May 2, 1980. Includes: Memorandum from Chancellor Clifton R. Wharton regarding the Proceedings of Convocation of Distinguished Faculty. Includes supporting papers. Opening Remarks by James E. Perdue, Vice Chancellor for Academic Programs, Policy and Planning. Academic Climate and Potential of the State Univeristy of New York by Dorothy Rogers. 16 pp. Academic Climate and Potential of the State University of New York by Kingsley L. Greene. 19 p Academic Climate and Potential of the State University of New York by Henry L. Bretton. 10 pp. Academic Climate and Potential of the State University of New York by Dr. Warren H. Thomas. State Unversity of New York Proposal for Honors Program. 6 pp. Remarks and Dialogue from Chancellor Clifton R. Wharton. 6 pp. President's Convocation. September 12, 1967. Bifold. Dr. Perdue, SUNY Oswego President. A Testimonial Luncheon and Reception in Honor of Dr. James E. Perdue. Trifold.
- Memorandums, 1966 - 1970 (Box-folder 1-7)
  Various college memos regarding policies, meetings, news releases, budgets, benefits, reports and administration issues. The memos were written between 1966 and 1977, with the highest concentration being during the mid-1970's. There are about 200 memos contained in three folders. Subjects include: Consortium Activity - Institutional Development Study Project. Speech by Samuel B. Gould - Mission and Purpose. Third Annual Faculty Assembly agenda and policies. Copy of "A Plan of Action" from Dr. Perdue. Promotions Procedures. Advisory Committee on the Selection of a Dean. Faculty salaries. Urban unrest. Campus student unrest. Proposed faculty bylaws. Registering students in programs prior to the time the programs have been approved. Movement for a moratorium on college activities. Equal Employment Opportunity. Term appointments for 1970-1971 academic year. Academic calendar changes. Wooden gavel made by Herbert S. Graves, class of 1930. Added to Dr. Sheldon's collection. Faculty library privileges. Local grievance procedures.
- Memorandums, 1971 - 1973 (Box-folder 1-8)
  Memorandums to and from Dr. Perdue pertaining to policies, meetings, news releases, budgets and administration issues. Subjects include: Report from Summer Conference Committee - "Freedom and Responsibility on Campus". Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation electrical line changes. Budget cuts. City of Oswego / Niagara Mohawk construction projects resulted in loss of 500 campus parking spaces. Faculty bylaws. State Dental Insurance Plan. Middle States Association and National Council for the Accreditation of Teacher Education. Oswego County United Fund Drive. New identification card for college community. Equal Employment Opportunity Policy Statement. Budget Bylaws Library staff and budget. Incident report. Hot line to Deputy to the Chancellor for major campus emergencies. State of New York Take Stock in America '72 Savings Bond Campaign. Travel expenses and use of automobiles policy statement. Microfilming machines usage. Microfilm Library Inventory. Safety Responsibilities. Anne Commerton appointed Acting Director of Libraries effective January 1, 1973. Recruitment Account Expenditures. First draft of local Master Plan submitted to Chancellor's Office. Annual reports. Reaction to State of College message. Call to faculty for upcoming faculty meeting - quorum needed. Vaccinia [Smallpox] Vaccination. Memo to all supervisors, re: summer responsibilities. Call to upcoming faculty meeting; new appointments listed. Seminar for Academic and Administrative Officers. 1973-1974 Campus Telephone Directory. Address by Professor Fred Hoyle. Personnel shifts. 1973-1974 faculty committee list. Criteria and procedures for Graduate Faculty membership. A Report on Energy Conservation Activities.
- Memorandums, 1974 - 1977 (Box-folder 1-9)
  Incoming and outgoing memorandums - Dr. Perdue pertaining to administration issues, meetings, policies, budgets and reports. Subjects include: Master Theses Energy / budget concerns Administrative Internship Program Equal Employment Opportunity Program Interviews for Executive Vice President and Provost positions. Annual Report formats. Memo from Lynn Hemink to All Classified Service Personnel concerning civil service law and attendance rules. Employee Tuition Waivers. New Faculty Orientation Sabbatical Leave. 1974-1975 College Directory. Personnel Responsibility Areas. Discretionary salary increases. 1974-1975 faculty committee list. American Council on Education Academic Administration Internship Program. Telephone tolls. Campus financial situation. Building temperatures Faculty Assembly bylaws. New York State Office of Employee Relations and CSEA negotiations impasse. Faculty and Staff Responsibilties in the Event of a Strike. Budget - 30% cut in telephone service. Travel expenses to SUNY-Wide Committees. Graduate Studies Dean vacancy. Temperature reduction in all campus buildings. Search for candidates for the position of Dean of Arts and Sciences.
- State of the College Message, 1967 - 1976 (Box-folder 1-10)
  State of the College Messages from 1967 to 1976. There are no reports contained here for 1972 and 1974. Each report is a summary of the framework, development and issues of the academic year.
- Reports, 1965 - 1973 (Box-folder 1-11)
  Reports "Report for October 1965" was submitted by Dr. Perdue to Samuel Gould, the President of S.U.N.Y. Albany. The report documents staff activities, curriculum, publications and research, student affairs. 8 pp. New York State Education Department Evaluation Report of the college. January 1970. 22 pp. "The College in Capsule - 1972-73" [3 pp] is an overview of the college regarding: New Academic Programs Student Health Services Student Government New Academic Appointments Oswego Overseas Hewitt Union Residence Hall Life Learning Resources Third Curriculum Community Service Center Facilities Programming
- Report to the Chancellor, 1971 - 1972 (Box-folder 1-12)
  The "President's Annual Report to the Chancellor" for 1971-72. The report was written by Dr. Perdue. 6 pp. Includes: Student Affairs, Academic Affairs and General Administration.
- Annual Report of the President, 1972 - 1976 (Box-folder 1-13)
  Annual Report of the President Annual Report of the President, 1972-1973. 21 pp. Includes: Academic Affairs Evaluation of Professional Faculty and Staff Student Enrollments Faculty Workload Role of Departmental Chairman Curricular Revision Center for the Improvement of Instruction Communication Administrative Reorganization Accountability Student Advisement Continuing Education Graduate Education Division of Arts and Sciences Division of Professional Studies Division of Graduate Studies Academic Support Services Administrative Affairs Student Affairs Graduate Admission Report, August 1972 - June 1973 Report on Proposals, July 1, 1972 - June 30, 1973 Schematic of Philosphy and Direction Division of Student Affairs Functional Organization chart. Annual Report of the President, 1973 - 1974. 12 pp. Includes: Overview College Calendar Enrollment Accomplishments and Direction Administrative Affairs Personnel Computer Center Auxiliary Services Security Maintenance & Operations Business Affairs Student Affairs Curricular Innovations and Revisions Program Revisions New and Revised Academic Policies Administrative appointments Department chairperson designations or redesignations. Selected Problems and Recommended Actions. Annual Report of the President, 1975 - 1976. 13 pp. Includes: Strategies for Survival Acadmic Affairs Curricular Innovations and Revisions Faculty Assembly actions Department chairperson designations or redesignations Academic Services Language Laboratory Learning Resources Center Penfield Library Personnel Office Student Financial Aids Veterans' Affairs Inservice Administrative Affairs Computer Center Campus Security Budget Office Maintenance Department Business Affairs Student Affairs Office of the President Equal Employment Opportunity College Development
- Presidential Review Report, 1969 - 1974 (Box-folder 1-14)
  Presidential Review Report 1969 - 1974 submitted by Dr. James E. Perdue, President, State University of New York College at Oswego. 30 pp. Includes: President's Statement of Self-Assessment, 1969-1974 Table of Contents: Prologue 1965-1969 Review 1969 - 1974, An Overview Time - Line Chart - following page 4 External Relationships Internal Relationships Institutions Tone Set by the President Administrative Leadership and Management Academic Leadership and Management Appendix -- A. Academic Programs Approved since 1969 B. Comparison of Projected Headcounts and FTE's to Actual Headcounts and FTE's C. Current projections through 1980 D. Total Faculty by numbers, ranks, degree preparation E. Comparative Budgets
- Presidential Purview Report, 1965 - 1978 (Box-folder 1-15)
  A Presidential Purview of S.U.N.Y. Oswego: Challenges, Changes and Accomplishments, 1965 to 1978 by James E. Perdue. 39 pp.
- Sponsored Research Report, 1981 (1-16)
  Nature and Needs of Sponsored Research in Four-Year Colleges and Two-Year Agricultural and Technical Colleges of the State University of New York". 37 pp. Handwritten note under title on title page, "Special project assigned to me by Chancellor 1981. JE Perdue." Contents: Introduction Improving Sponsored Research Faculty Criticisms From Two-Year Colleges Faculty Suggestions For Improvement From Two-Year Colleges Faculty Criticisms From Four-Year Colleges Faculty Suggestions For Improvement From Four-Year Colleges Conclusions and Recommendations Faculty Questionnaire
- Consultancy, 1970 (Box-folder 1-17)
  Consultancy A report for a consultancy which Perdue participated in for Robert Finch, the Counsellor to the President of the United States. The report is entitled "Selected Problems Facing Higher Education in the 1970's", dated November 2, 1970. 34 pp. The report was pieced together by 6 consultants total (including Dr. Perdue). Also included are 2 items of correspondence, 1 memorandum and a newpaper article regarding the project.
- Correspondence, 1963 - 1990 (Box-folder 1-18)
  The next 10 folders contain various personal and professional correspondence ranging from 1963 to 1990. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. This first folder contains incoming and outgoing [although most correspondence is carbon copies of typed outgoing correspondence from Dr. Perdue] correspondence pertaining to his 1965 move from Colorado to Oswego, New York, including congratulations and acknowledgements. The correspondence is in chronological order.
- Correspondence, 1966 - 1971 (Box-folder 1-19)
  Correspondence from students, and correspondence pertaining to speaking engagements, etc. Incoming and outgoing. Typed and handwritten. In chronological order. Also included is a typed quote by Dr. Richard Piez.
- Correspondence, 1965 - 1977 (Box-folder 1-20)
  SUNY Oswego related correspondence. Incoming and outgoing. Typed, including carbon copies. In chronological order.
- Correspondence, 1963 - 1965 (Box-folder 1-21)
  Correspondence pertains to early Oswego contact, trip expenses and SUNY Oswego information. Chronologically ordered. Incoming and outgoing typed correspondence, some on carbon paper. Correspondents include: Harry W. Porter, Provost, State University of New York, Albany, New York. Harry E. Charlton, Director of Public Information, State University College, Oswego, New York. George M. Penney, Chairman of the College Council, State University College, Oswego. Charles F. Wells, Acting Secretary, College Council, State University College, Oswego. Dr. Charles S. Turner, Acting President, State University College, Oswego. Dr. Kenneth E. Young, President, State University College, Cortland, New York. W.H. Cowley, David Jacks Professor of Higher Education, Stanford Univeristy. J. Lawrence Murray, Vice President, State University of New York, Albany, New York. Clarence Leighton, Oswego Palladium-Times, Oswego, New York. Miss Helen Hagger, College Librarian, State University of New York, Oswego, New York Dr. Leonard G. Boonin, Associate Professor of Philosophy, State University College, Oswego. William Adams, President, Associated Student Body, State University College, Oswego. Dr. J. Sherwood Dunham, Acting Dean, State University College, Oswego, New York. Dr. Emmet C. Stopher, Chairman, Department of Mathematics, State University College. David G. Berry, Director, Atmospheric Science Research Center, SUNY, Albany. Dr. Joseph Leese, Professor of Education, SUNY @ Albany. Dr. Jack L. Nelson, School of Education, SUNY @ Buffalo. Mrs. George L. Richardson, Syracuse, New York. Dr. Erwin Palmer, Academic Advisory Committee, SUC, Oswego, New York. Dr. James E. Allen, Jr., Office of the Commissioner, SUNY, SED, Albany, New York. Roman Tratch, Department of Psychology, State University of New York College, Oswego. Mrs. Ben H. Bohall, Oswego, New York Rev. Richard F. Ryan, S.J., President of Regis College, Denver, CO. Rev. Robert E. Hall, Chaplain, Newman Hall Catholic Center, Oswego, New York Virginio L. Piucci, Acting Director, Division of Elementary + Secondary School Education, SUCO Carl James Holmes, Syracuse, New York. Dr. Robert W. Rock, Dean of Students, State University College at Oswego Kenneth E. Dawson, Executive Secretary-Treasurer, American IA Association, Inc. The Sisters of Theta Chi Rho, Oswego, New York. Shirley Walker, Funnelle Hall, SUCO Mary Brown, Secretary to the President, State University College at Oswego Dr. W. Seward Salisbury, Chairman, Department of Social Studies, SUCO Dr. Leonard Becker, Administrative Assistant, SUCO Dr. Gardner Wells, SUCO President, Sigma Gamma Fraternity, SUCO Edward P. Boardway, President, Civil Service Employees Assoc., Inc., Oswego Chapter
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 1-22)
  Evaluation of the Chief Administrative Office, 1974, evaluates the Perdue administration at SUNY Oswego. Includes memorandums from: Lynn D. Hemink Donald R. Mathieu, Chairman, Faculty Assembly Correspondence from: James S. Smoot, Vice Chancellor for University-Wide Services and Special Programs, Albany, New York. - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - Faculty Evaluation of Chief Administrative Officer invitation/directive. May 6, 1974. Administrative Evaluation of President Perdue. May, 1974. 3 pp. Evaluation of the President's Performance. (Minority Report by the Students). 11 pp.
- Correspondence, 1977 (Box-folder 1-23)
  Correspondence pertains to Dr. Perdue's move from Oswego to Albany, New York. Correspondence between Dr. Perdue and Ernest L. Boyer.
- Correspondence, 1977 - 1981 (Box-folder 1-24)
  Correspondence - Dr. George T. Land and others. Handwritten note from JE Perdue, "Some of my correspondence with Dr. George T. Land - author, consultant and lecturer at universities and businesses such as General Motors. Geo and I did several things together at a number of colleges". Correspondence is arranged chronologically. 1977 - 1981. Handwritten and typed. Correspondents in addition to Dr. Land: President Donald E. Walker, Southeastern Massachusetts University, North Dartmouth, Mass. Attached to correspondence is a 1977 seven-page article, "The Halitosis Strategy of Survival" by Donald E. Walker. George Keller, SEARCH, A journal of scholarly research. Dr. Gabriele L. Rico, School of Humanities + the Arts, San Jose State University, San Jose, CA Attached is a five-page "studen evalution of clustering." Clifton R. Wharton, Jr., Chancellor, SUNY, Albany, New York.
- Correspondence-Robert Greenleaf, 1977 - 1990 (Box-folder 1-25)